啊！我宣佈，言訊繼續進行。
下一位提問嘅係李卓人議員。
誒，多謝主席。首先就誒，頭先李主席你都問咗一個誒問題咧，就佢話遲啲會答覆嘅，即係關於個誒所謂integrated master plan個問題。噉我就係想即係希望佢遲啲答覆嗰時答埋一樣嘢咧，就係佢哋誒而家如果佢哋畀咗咁冇問題啦。咁但係我哋一路。
信息都係路政署係冇依個master plan嘅，咁誒，如果冇路政署冇master plan咁揀，咁可能係冇畀到，咁等間佢翻嚟check啦。咁但係如果誒佢哋第一路政署有冇問過佢哋，或者Jacob有冇問過佢哋攞嘢integrate master plan？
係嚇咁呢個可能佢而家都達唔到嘅，因為佢要翻去睇嚇。咁希望佢補充嗰時候補充埋呢樣嘢嚇。好，梁生，你可唔可以補充埋呢樣嘢？即係如果係冇提供畀政府嘅話咧，噉佢哋有冇向你哋誒要求提供過啊？啊，Yes，we'll check and review it.唔該，好多謝主席。噉啊，跟住我想問翻個問題咧，就係即係。
誒喺即係今日聖經裏邊第六第七段咧，其實就即係誒而家好清楚表示咧，就係其實成個工程環境係好多挑戰。
嚇，亦都係咧就誒嗰個誒複雜性咧係好誒significant啊，即係好好好好好犀利啦，好重要啦嚇。咁既然係而家講到好似好睏難噉。
咁當時佢哋接呢個嘅協議嘅時候。
嚇！咁當然佢頭先答個方法就係話啊，第三者都話doable but tight啊。
噉我從一個接協議嘅人啊，我我係作為一個港鐵，如果我對我自己嘅機構負責任嘅話咧，即係我自己都應該爭取一個寬鬆啲嘅一個嘅時間表嘅。
或者寬鬆啲嘅誒，即係價價價錢嘅，咁但係好似咧就係誒港鐵嗰方面咧，就即係乜都拍心口噉。
咁到底我想問一個問題就係，到底係港鐵你自己去當時嘅工程團隊前總裁自視過高，乜都拍心口咧？
定係有另一個可能性嘅，即係有兩個可能性啊，就係誒嗰啲雖然係好緊。
嚇！好大挑戰，早知我覺得我搞得掂。
一個可能性係噉。
第二個可能性咧，就係政府拍佢哋膊頭。
嚇！政府話：喂，我點都係要呢個時間表做起㗎啦。嚇，你儘量做啦。咁點困難你都做啦。嚇，唔掂嗰時做唔掂嗰時，咪大家咪睇下點樣喺個言裏邊啊啊！我哋政府去咩氣咯噉樣。咁到底個情況？
當時接個協議嘅時候，係佢哋自視過高咧。
定係政府係向對施壓又好，氹又好嚇，叫佢哋跟翻個時間表去做，係一個所謂政府嘅面子工程多啲咧噉樣。噉我想問翻佢哋，到底當時係誒接個協議嗰陣時做個entrustment嘅時候啊啊！
委託協議嘅時候，佢哋本身係到底係邊個情況啊？你講嘅係邊一方面？係咪嗰個工程嗰個完工時期時間定係兩樣時間同錢同埋錢嚇時間同錢都係嘅，因為當錢佢頭先都答過話，佢哋大加大個應急啦嚇。但係個時間亦都係第三個party都講話。
話替㗎嘛，講明係替㗎嘛。咁如果我作為一個即係畀人委託嘅人，喂，我梗係希望寬鬆啲㗎。
除非佢覺得自視過高啫嘛，定係即係成日定係政府畀壓力，即係兩兩兩個可能性啊。係關於呢個工程開支同埋個時間表嘅問題咧，係地鐵公司、港鐵公司係過分自信啦，定係因為受壓嚇，所以就作出噉嘅安排。啊，thank you，Chairman。
For and honourable member for that question, as we have mentioned, there was a significant amount of work done prior to entering into the second entrustment agreement, and there were a number of third parties involved. Those third parties also looked at, amongst other things, the timetable as well as the cost.
At the end of the day, there was a.
結論， at that time that the timetable was doable but tight. I would highlight for members a particular paragraph in the IEP report. This is government's IEP report. This is paragraph two hundred and fifty four on page sixty five. And to answer the honourable member's question, if chairman would.
indulge me, I quote that paragraph.
This is from the Price Waterhouse facture annexure to the IEP report, which in paragraph 254 said, and I quote: "We have not had sight of any evidence during the study that indicates government put pressure on MTRCL to tighten the delivery schedule prior to EA2, although."
We understand from MTRCL that government was keen to complete the Hong Kong section as early as possible, and discussions were held between Railway Development Office and MTRCL on this topic. The timetable, as highlighted, was at that time seemed to be doable but tight.
係啦，即係咁變成係。如果係噉，即係話唔係政府壓力啦。噉係會唔會而家睇即係你哋曾經都講過嚇，即係其實會唔會係工程團隊啊，係自視過高咧？根本即係根本冇個咁緊嘅。然後跟住而家第六第七段，你又講到話咁困難啦，係咪？
啊！即係變成你哋喺判斷嘅時候係誒輕率，誒係誒將個困難係誒冇睇。
誒冇冇去好即係正視嘅困難，然後誒自視過高，而令到你哋覺得可以喺呢個時間同埋錢嗰度去接呢個嘅協議啦嚇。
Do a bit of price咧評估係咪因為自視過高嘅評估咧？
honourable member chairman, I would once again, this is quoting from government's own IEP report in paragraph two five five. They go on to say that, and this is factually, that MTR has sought assurance from our design consultants on the achievability of the timetable, the timelines in two thousand nine during both the
preliminary design as well as the detailed design stages.
It is understood from these studies that the consultants were asked by MTR to develop construction programmes, contracts and advice on the construction methodologies. I would further respond to the member's question on the basis that the challenges that we have mentioned, a number of these challenges pertain across the industry.
Some of these challenges were recognised at the beginning. The highlighted in both the IBC and the IEP report was comments back in 09 of the potential of not being able to get sufficient labour. However, as we went through the construction piece, the extent, the extent
of these challenges were much more than had originally been anticipated. An example of that is, as highlighted in the IDC report, when
at the beginning back in 2009, using government indices looking at construction costs, there was an assumption that labour costs will only be increasing at around two or three percent, construction costs at two or three percent per annum. In fact, over that same period of time, construction costs were increasing.
Significantly more than that, and in some cases double digit per annum. So the issues, some of the challenges were recognised at the beginning. However, the extent and magnitude of those challenges continued to develop over the course of the project, and were an industry wide situation.
係。
阿梁生，即係我跟進翻一下個問題就係，即係一個咁龐大咁複雜工程。即係如果你係最初評估係一個doable but tight嘅話咧，咁其實本身已經係一個即係會工程係有好多預計唔到嘅嘢㗎嘛。咁如果一個咁龐大嘅工程嘅話咧，如果你話do
一開始已經覺得佢係double betty嘅話，呢個係咪本身已經係一個太過樂觀嘅一個估計咧？
嗯。
Chairman, of course, in addition to the consultants that were working on this project, the contractors that were tendering the various contracts were also at that time of the view that the timetable of the programme was achievable. I would, however, highlight that obviously this is now with the benefit of hindsight, the I.
IBC report, the IBC reported, the IBC report noted that.
The.
That.
And I quote: the negative impact of the unforeseen events on the schedule was not so much caused by any flaw in engineering or project management as by a lack of adequate schedule contingency. This is actually one of the conclusions from the IBC report.
咪但係係啦。咁如果用翻頭先嗰個話，即係誒最後嗰句啊。咁其實誒個I B C report就係話你lack of schedule。最後個字係咩？我聽唔到lack of schedule。嗯，termin the lack of adequate schedule contingency。
係啦，咁好啦。咁如果即係講到咧，最後唔係初初個問題啦，噉啊講到係中間係跟住lack of schedule contingency，即係你應變嗰個誒誒能力，或者應變嗰個即係緩充有啲緩時間嘅緩充啦，係啦，緩充時間唔夠噉，但係。
係等於即即初初哇，好低咁噉。佢而家嘅schedule嘅嗰個誒condition係唔夠啦嚇。咁其實會唔會其實睇翻根本成單成件事就係依一句咧，係倒翻轉係證明到本身係誒成個時間表梯到一個地步，根本冇可能應急到。
咁而你哋咁大龐大嘅工程啊，冇可能唔畀多啲寬鬆啲嘅，嗯，即係時間出嚟咧，係去應急咁好。我又倒翻轉問啦，咁點解你哋嗰時唔爭取一個冇咁梯嘅、冇咁緊嘅，有多啲誒scale用翻你嘅字眼誒？
schedule contingency應急時間表嘅方法係去誒，即係開始嗰時同政府要求個時間比較耐啲咧。
點解唔要求一個durable but not so tight嘅時間表？Thank you, honorable member and chairman for that question. The
One looks back at the previous successes of the MTR projects. MTR has over the last thirty odd years successfully delivered projects on time and on budget, using the systems and processes which we use also for the Express Rail Link, with certain adjustments.
the is based on the previous successes that.
我 believe led the team and all of us to believe that, despite the fact that the schedule was doable but tight, that it was doable.
即係過去嘅成功，令佢哋即係麻木啦。即係如果咁講，用翻總結嚟講，啊，多謝主席。
下一位林嘉標議，多謝主席。啊，因為今日跌咗幾個會咧，所以我唔肯定我問嘅問題會唔會同其他委員會重複。
誒，我諗兩個方面啦，即係成件事誒幾個嘅，即係誒檢討嘅報告都講出啲問題。譬如我引述啊，運房局副局長咧，邱食武先生喺一五年四月廿八號我嘅言訊裏面曾經講過嘅，對於工程隊伍實際情況嘅掌握，講。
港鐵本身嘅高層或者政府，其實都唔掌握。
佢哋喺交代資料方面咧，即係話咧，佢哋掌握嘅工程進度以及佢哋向上層或者港府路政署作出嘅報告，其實並非完全反映情況，或者佢哋有啲計劃都未必完全畀政府知道。
咁亦都有另一個咧，係由啊特首委任嘅一個嘅啊誒法官去做嗰個主席嘅誒檢查報告，亦都有噉樣嘅類似嘅描述，即係話咧誒經過一啲嘅啊瞭解咧，甚至引述阿周大創作為當時嘅工程總監咧，都話佢完全咧係失敗。
都唔能夠掌握個情況，我就所以想問阿梁生咧，究竟即係兩個問題，據你嘅瞭解，整個架構裏面究竟邊一個職位係最掌握高鐵嘅進度咧？即係喺發生呢個即係誒所謂誤誒謠誤正式披露之。
前同而家之後有冇唔同咧？第二樣嘢就係我頭先所引述啊，邱成武副局長所講嘅陳述。
就話港鐵公司不完全畀政府當局知道，係咪希望隱瞞工程實際進度？噉你又點睇咧？呢兩個問題。
係啊。
嗯。
主席，once again, there is never. There's always been full disclosure of information to government and the various departments of government, and at no time was there ever any intent, nor would there ever be any intent to withhold any information. I think the comment from Mr. Yao.
姚松茂，when when he appeared in front of the select committee, also refers to the IBC report and that same question which was answered by or asked to Mr. K. K. Lau and Mr. Henry Chang. This was in November two thousand and thirteen.
When the project was obviously still ongoing, and this was during a period when
MTR was seeking final was seeking from the contractor of a very important contract eight hundred and ten A the schedule to complete under this minimum operating requirement approach and until we have until MTR had that information it is very difficult to.
confirm or come up with final comments on the schedule. So at that time in November two thousand and thirteen, which I believe is what Mr Yau Sing Mo was referring to, MTR and our project team was still awaiting the response from the contractor of eight hundred and ten A on the.
program.
With regards to the honourable member's second question, the as members are aware, with and highlighted in our
Various reports, the we have a clear process and system in place in terms of.
In project management of the express rail link, we're regular reporting to government as well as other entities. Of course, with the
Whether benefit of hindsight, and with the IBC report, the IBC report have came up, come up with some recommendations in terms of enhancement to our system, and we've implemented those recommendations.
作為我之前提到，那些建議包括設立一個基建委員會，現在已經成立並運作，以及加強報告架構，這包括使用所謂的交通燈以及里程碑。所以這些加強措施已經實施。
Thank you, Chairman。啊，我我想我我想問嘅問咧，頭先個問題，即係話，起碼我要一條畫線咧，就係話，你哋嘅董事局自己都有個即係檢討嘅委員會，並且作出一啲嘅建議。我用你呢呢條線作準則喺呢個啊檢討之前，最熟知。
呢個工程進度嘅會係港鐵邊一個嘅啊職務嘅人咧？會唔會就係周大倉總監？定係連佢自己都唔知係咪自己應該係掌握最清楚咧？而喺檢討之後，究竟又應該邊一個同事或者邊一個小組係最熟知呢個工程嘅進度咧？
As we've highlighted in our responses to the select committee, the the way MTR operates, like many companies, the board is overall responsible for the activities of MTR, but delegates the management of day-to-day business to the
Executive, the executive furthermore has particular directors that look at particular aspects of the business. One of those aspects, of course, is the importantly the project aspects of the business. Within the project team, there are many colleagues. There are three thousand colleagues in the project team, and the structure and reporting.
Of that project team, Einstein have been in the various reports and have been reported to the select committee. The
The project director ultimately is responsible to the executive and to the board, and through that to the board, looking at the progress of all the projects that MTR is undertaking.
As I mentioned, now with the enhanced structure, we have in addition, the board has set up the capital works committee that would also have reports from the projects director in the projects division.
啊總啊總監，我我想問，即係未加強呢個架構之前，係咪就係存在咗一啲嘅問題？就係負責做呢個西鐵嘅誒，做呢個高鐵嘅工程嘅負責人負責嘅同時，係攬住所有資訊，連你以及董事局都唔知咧。
先生，the as as I mentioned, the way MTR the the way the governance of the company operates, the individual directors are responsible for their particular areas, and the individual directors report on a regular basis to the executive of MTR and the executive in.
Return report to the board. That is the the method of reporting. I would highlight, and this is highlighted in the IBC report, that perhaps because of the overoptimism of the project director and the project team, it was not until April, until April of 2014, that the delay of the express rail.
Link beyond 2015 was reported to the executive committee and to government.
係個董事局都係嗰時候先知嘅，係咪咧？啊，That is absolutely correct, Chairman. That it was only啊in April of 2014。係鄧家彪議員。
嗱。
一個就係你嘅架構裏面嗰啲嘅啊溝通或者協作嘅關係嘅一啲嘅缺失，另一個咧就係喺呢個架構裏面有責任同政府相關部門路政處嘅溝通上面，我哋都係特別重點去睇。尤其上個禮拜裏面，我哋係邀請。
咗啊！陳志恩啊，鐵路拓展處處長，我亦都再引述咧。誒，佢嘅講法就係話喺個陳述書又好，或者喺個啊言訊嘅過程裡面都係咁講。喺有啲情況底下咧，路政處未能適時噉樣獲得該等資料，港鐵公司嘅獨立董事委員會第一份報告近日。
正一件事實，就是項目團隊曾對路政署保留咗有關項目進度嘅關鍵資訊。
啊，總監，我想了解誒，你同唔同意陳志恩處長嘅講法，以及你點樣睇乜嘢為之關鍵資訊？
啊。
Thank you for that question. As the honourable member mentioned, the comments from the IBC report and the IBC report did note that in the in November there was certain voices from the project within the project.
team that was questioning the doability of the 2015 schedule, but as I mentioned as I mentioned before, at that time, this is in November 2013. At that time, we MTR and the project team, as I understand it.
We're still getting from the contractor, from the eight hundred and ten A contractor, a programme. Without that programme, it is very difficult to assess the assess the the effectiveness of the overall programme to complete the project. So at that time.
And I think the comment from Mr. Henry Chang was relating to that particular period when the project team was still trying to get a final programme from the A10A contractor.
誒，我最後一個補充啫。我我哋嘅感覺，即係我唔知其他委員係咪同意，陳志恩處長所描述，就係話佢想攞一啲關鍵資料，其實有啲真係好關鍵，譬如個工程嘅改動，係經常覺得都係港鐵畀唔曬全部，或者佢都會諗啊，係咪仲有更多？呢個唔係。
講緊單一嘅事件或者單一嘅場合，而係佢嘅一個普遍嘅一個經驗。我我我我聽到係嘅嗰個情況係噉啊，所以呢，總監，我想問，即係呢個普遍嘅情況，你同唔同意啊？嗯誒啊，Honourable Member Chairman，as we have as I've
mentioned and as highlighted in the various reports, we are provided information as required by government. There was significant, very significant.
對話、互換、 discussions、 meetings with government and members of government throughout the process. and as we've also mentioned, government have appointed their M and V consultant Jacobs to review and audit the work which MTR has done. so there was a significant exchange of information.
During all this period, as I commented earlier, the
IBC report also noted that government and MTR were working in a collaborative and cooperative manner.
咁如果聽你咁講，梁生咁應該係誒，因為。
特愛大家都呢個委員會都聽過咧，就係。
誒政府方面嘅人員咧，就係都幾強調咧，就係唔係強調啦嚇，只要提過咧。
就係港鐵公司嗰方面咧，係冇提提供所有足夠嘅或者全部嘅資料，使到佢作出一個即係有效嘅評估。噉你而家話你係完全係冇隱瞞啊，或者係一個好即係好暢順嘅一個溝通嘅話，噉係變咗係即係。
即係政府方面嘅講法咧，有少少係隱瞞嘅喎，係咪即係有少少係即係唔係太過誠實咧？誒，Chairman，I cannot comment on other people's comments. But however, what I would like to do is once again quote from the IBC report. The IBC had
reviewed and investigated this matter at length, including their independent experts. And if Chairman would indulge me, just very quickly, the IPC in their report, and this is in paragraph one three seven of the first IPC report, page thirteen, says delays.
關於這個項目計劃，已經報告在及時和準確地向政府，根據委託協議的條款。事實上，進一步在第83頁第5.32段的第一次IBC報告中，它説出IBC不認為。
任何嘗試由項目團隊或合作夥伴嚟掩蓋或隱瞞正在發生嘅各種項目合同嘅延誤。多謝主席。
更加不如原狀無問。
胡志偉議員。
多主席。
誒，我個提問可能有啲都有同事提問過，幫我嘗試係即係再做誒。我我想問下咧，獨立專家小組報告喺第六點一一段咧係指出，由於政府係無從根據一個全面綜合並且係以整個項目為本嘅工程總綱計劃去接收匯報。
所以一直咧係被蒙在鼓裏。
報告第六點一八段咧，亦都指出，彙報唔清晰嘅問題咧，係引致政府係過度信賴港鐵公司缺乏理據嘅保證，誤以為咧係追回進度嘅措施係的確有效，可以令高鐵香港段嘅項目如期進工。我想問下阿梁生或者港鐵。
公司對獨立專家小組呢個評價咧，你係咪同意佢呢一個評價？同埋你對於呢個評價咧有啲乜嘢嘅回應？咁呢個係第一條，或者答咗先啊嘛嚇，梁生。
Yeah. Once again, Chairman.
In terms of disclosure of information, I think we have discussed that already. There is a significant amount of discussions, disclosure as well as meetings with government and government officials, as well as through the so-called M and V consultant Jacobs.
In the audit and review of the status of the project and the progress of the project. And once again, and as the honourable member had mentioned, in terms of the master programme, our IBC experts and ourselves are.
會説那有master，有master programmes，which are updated on a periodic basis using this P6 Primavera software，that is a requirement under our project management processes。
主席，我其實個問題係你同唔同意專家小組呢一個評價？
兩位淨係答同意定係唔同意？I think, Chairman, we at MTR we had cooperated significantly with the IEP and their experts. In general, we agree with the the factual findings of the IEP, which are highlighted in the appendix to the IEP.
Report, there are certain aspects of the the recommendations and the comments from the IEP which we take a
different view on.
okay。
政府就有就住成個係誒工程咧，就委任咗積合社係作為一個監核顧問公司，噉佢當然可以向港鐵公司咧係去索取資料嘅。
我想問下，港鐵公司係咪百分之一百咧？係向加密顧問公司提供所有即及所要求嘅所有資料，有冇作任何篩選？
啊。
To my knowledge, chairman, to my knowledge, all the information, and this is to my knowledge, all the information that have been requested by government and their M and V consultant have been provided accordingly. That that is my knowledge and understanding from reviewing all the various reports that have been made available to the public.
O.K.
咁即係話誒，如果我哋嚟緊可能同呢個即係討論家科嘅時候傳召佢上嚟嘅話，咁誒可能會得到唔同嘅一個圖像，都唔定係咪咩意思啊？因為係退弱knowledge啊嘛。
主席，作為議員，作為您所知，我並未直接參與當時的項目團隊，所以我的知識是現有的，包括公眾可獲取的資訊，這表明所有資訊都已提供。
胡志偉議，我諗係即係我哋冇估計啦。明白，多謝唔緊要。啊，主席，我我其實想誒翻問另一個部分，因為咧啊梁生咧過往係港鐵嘅係財務總監嚟嘅，噉我想問下就係即係根據啊陳述書嘅第六段啦，就係港鐵高鐵。
咧喺香港段咧，係首個以服務經營權嘅模式咧建造嘅香港鐵路項目嚟嘅。噉就誒，我想問下就係你作為前財務總監，你有冇就住呢個部分，呢個全新嘅模式去建造高鐵香港段，係進行個分析？
財務分析風險嘅係評估，提供咗乜嘢資料畀港鐵公司咧？係就住呢個工程咧，係作你作一個財務總監嘅時候，嗰個嘅係分析嘅報告。
係兩三。
Chairman, there are very clear processes in place at MTR to assess projects as and to monitor projects as they develop.
not forgetting that under the entrustment agreement we are to use our project management systems and processes which include amongst others the PIMS as well as our financial controls our procurement processes these processes have been reviewed and audited by a number of third parties and those.
reviews and audits commend the effectiveness of that process. As I have said previously, at MTR we use the same process and procedures for all our projects, be they service concession projects like this Express Rail Link, or be they ownership projects like the South Island Line East. We use the
The same process in all our assessment. That same process would be in accordance with our project management, our financial management, our procurement, etc.
即係我我係想直接問財務總監，即係當其實在財務總監嘅時間，有冇做過一個係即係風險評估誒嗰個嘅係報告咧，係交過畀董事會。
非常，thank you, member for that question. Yes, there was of course significant review of the entrustment agreement, and the board, as highlighted in the IEP report, also discussed the entrustment agreement.
at that point in time in back in 2009, I
我和 others are the view that the entrustment agreement has a reasonable sharing of risk and reward between MTR as the project manager, as the project manager, as well as government as the owner of the project.
主席，我唔知可唔可以向呢個係即係前財務總監即係梁生咧，係即係索取到呢一份嘅係誒風險同埋當其時嘅財務分析嘅報告，因為我相信都係好重要嘅參考資料咧。去顯示就話港鐵係從一個乜嘢角度咧去考慮，即係呢一個一個doable but tight嘅一個project。
係誒誒，梁生。
Once again, the doable but tight in terms of timetable. That was the based on significant amount of work also done with and by third parties looking at the timetable, and is based on that that the that the conclusion or the recommendation of doable but.
tight arose.
There was, as I mentioned, and this is highlighted in the IEP report discussion at at the MTR board on the entrustment agreement, which also looks at the risk of the entrustment agreement.
即係每事我聽唔清楚，噉係咪可以可以提供？你講doable but tight，你講嘅個時間表啊嘛。唔係而家講緊財務安排嘅話咧，係即係個風險評估嘅話咧，咁要同即係我想問一問，就係同我哋嗰個而家嗰個調查嗰個範圍係邊一部分係有關？主席，我我諗我要噉樣睇嘅，第一。
就係誒喺嗰份entrustment agreement裏邊咧，其實大家都有討論呢個係doable but tight呢一個概念啦。
咁同埋都有，我哋需要係處理嗰個會唔會有超支個問題。咁喺個Entrustment Agreement裏邊咧，就有一個好重要嘅條款，就係政府係會承擔咧。如果有需要嘅話咧，係額外嘅開支嘅。噉我想知道就係話，當其時成個風險評估對於喺呢份Entrustment Agreement裏邊嘅呢啲條。
款咧，其實係作為財務總監，佢點樣去睇，會畀即係會帶嚟畀港鐵作為個上市公司嘅一個風險評估，同一時間就係去平衡翻去接呢個政府project嘅時間佢嘅睇法。所以我從呢個角度去睇嘅。你係意思係同佢同嗰個現引起嘅超支係有？
評喺個評估裏邊係咪嘅意思啊？冇錯，係梁生。
Chairman, as I mentioned, there there was a due process in place to review all our projects, including importantly the express rail link. And as I mentioned, there were a number of discussions with government that ultimately resulted in the programme to complete and the the cost to.
complete, both government and ourselves having appointed third parties to look at these matters. So the risk assessment of the overall project was an ongoing matter that over the course of the period prior to the signing of the entrustment agreement.
即係換言之，就係誒我阿梁生唔可以提供到佢當其時所作嘅呢個risk assessment嘅report。OK，明白。
就誒，勞政處處長、前勞政處處長阿魏志誠先生咧，喺我哋六月二號嘅言訊咧，係指出，即係成個項目咧係有嘅四廿幾份嘅唔同嘅合約嘅。
咁當我哋考慮呢啲詳細分析嘅時間咧，係應該要睇埋除咗個完工期之外，睇埋個開工期。如果開工期遲咗嘅話咧，開員工期又冇調整嘅話，緩衝期自然就會少咗。
我想問下，就係喺港鐵而家呢四廿幾份嘅高鐵呢四廿幾份嘅合約裏邊，有幾多份嘅合約咧係未能夠如期開工？若果開工期延遲咗嘅話，港鐵公司有冇同呢啲承建商咧就完工期作出相應嘅調整？如果冇，又會唔會成為多份合約工期？
出現滯後嘅原因，甚至就係話係一啲claims嘅基礎咧。
嗯，啊，thank you。
Honourable member, for that question, as as members are aware, it is the express rail link is a highly complicated project with a number of the construction contracts that are interlinked.
One contract could have an impact on another contract. The
highlighted in the various reports is a comment that in particular one contract was tendered out late. This is contract eight ten A or later than originally originally.
propose or originally anticipated.
also highlighted in the IEP report, the and the IBC report, when the contract was tendered out, the contractors. In fact, there were a number of contractors tendering for that contract. The contractors were of the view that the timetable was doable, despite the fact that the completion date, as as the honourable member said.
The completion date was not shifted back, so there was a compression of timetable to achieve the same completion date. When those contracts were, or that particular contract was tendered up, the contractors were of the view that the shorter timetable was doable.
主席，我就想問兩個問，我想問一問阿梁生，或者係你答問題嗰時咧，你最好就答自己嘅問題，自己所知嘅嘢答，就唔需要太引述太多啲報告，因為我哋想攞到嘅係你嘅答案，唔係嘅嗰個報告裏邊嘅答案啊，好嘛？
多主席，我諗其實我呢個其中一個好重要，我一路聽都係梁生都引述翻報告嘅答案。噉我我唔知其實梁生係知幾多，定係佢只不過係一個錄音機咧，係報告翻報告所講嘅內容。咁誒，但我兩點啊，第一個就係話頭先我哋問到阿梁生都有講到，就係話合約同合約之間有好多interlink嘅。
呢啲interlink啊！
誒喺現時，我哋所見到嘅係誒超支延誤超支嘅部分咯。我諗講緊即係因為延誤引致嘅超支嘅問題，誒會唔會構成咗即係承建商索償嘅其中一個好重要嘅元素招致嘅嘢？呢個第一個，第二個就係話我哋都問過。
個路政署佢見到港鐵為咗追趕呢個落後、追趕延誤嗰個嘅係工作嘅時間咧，有時係會透過係改動嘅設計咧，係去進行嘅。咁路政署嘅講法就係話誒呢啲改動延誤，佢哋只係comments啫，唔係一個。
審批，我想問下樑生，你又點樣理解路政署係去comments on？
誒港鐵喺高鐵工程裏邊所提交嘅一啲更動設計嘅要求，而你只係得到一個叫做comment嘅時間，喺你哋眼中呢個係咪等於同意？
政府已經approve咗呢一個嘅安排，咁如果誒？
正常一個approval嘅程序應該點樣樣？都請你解釋一下。
先生，no，thank you for that question. We have at MTR a very clear and time time tried system in assessing claims as well as discussions with contractors on claims because of the.
Commercial sensitivity relating to claims. I'm at this time not able to comment more with regards to claims or individual claims.
The honourable member also asked a question with regards to delay recovery measures, the so-called DRM. Once again, there's a clear process in place, and that's highlighted in the reports. The process ultimately would have those DRM's, the delay recovery measures, going for approval in what we call the project control.
Group PCG，this PCG Project Control Group is a an internal MTR group that assesses amongst other things changes as well DRMs as well as claims.
政府官員是被邀請，並坐席作為觀察員在PCG，當涉及有關快速鐵路連接和沙田中央連接的所謂委託項目正在討論時。政府成員被邀請。
要comment on matters relating to those projects at the P.C.G.
誒，我想澄清翻係咪即係話，如果government officials喺個P.C.G. group裏邊係冇反對一個嘅係delay recovery measures嘅話，噉就等於係一個政府同意嘅安排。
Chairman, as members are aware, under the entrustment agreement, MTR has to use our processes as adjusted in terms of governance and communication with government. Very clearly, one of those processes, and also highlighted in the piece.
在entrustment agreements would be MTR's assessment of claims as well as matters like delay recovery measures. Government and government members have access to all the relevant PCG papers, the papers that discuss and talk about either the express rail link.
或The Schatten to Central Link， and at the P.C.G. meetings， they are invited relating to those matters to give their views。
喺PCG嗰個係meeting水邊呢啲DRM。
嘅會induce嘅cause，政府係咪會知悉嘅？
As I understand in these PCG papers relating to the delay recovery measures, in addition to the discussion on the effectiveness of the the measures and the technical aspects of the measures, these papers will include will include the
financial impact of these delay recovery measures.
As I understand it，好誒主席，我因為其實過程裏邊咧都牽涉到好多嘅呢啲D R M嘅measures嘅噉，但係似乎政府一路都唔係好嗱喺我哋嘅調查裏邊咧，就唔係好aware到就係去裏邊involve嘅course。咁但係頭先阿梁生就講就係話咧。
每一個呢啲meetings，每一個D.R.M嘅measures咧，都會involve cost implications嘅。我我想睇下樑生有冇辦法係可以提供到呢一度嘅證明畀我哋睇，就係話喺呢啲P即係呢啲嘅P.C.G嘅meeting水平咧，誒高鐵嘅承建過程裏邊咧，係會將所有D.R.M measures嘅。
嘅係cost implications嘅文件係呈交咗畀政府，係知悉。
佢有冇咁做啊？有冇噉樣做？係梁生，佢話有做嘅，但係我想問下有冇有個證據啊？畀到我哋咁解啫。
佢講嘅咪證據咯。
你有冇咁做啊，梁生？啊，徐明，once again，嗰個即係嗰個即係由呢個言誤引發出嚟嘅DRM所涉及嘅超，即係個即係比正常開支係超出正常開支嘅款項咧，有冇向政府報告啊？即係每每一部分都係一個。
睇下啲人點睇。主席，Once again, the
financial aspects, timing aspects and the criticality of the DRMs are all set out in the PCG papers, which are made available to government. These papers are then discussed at the particular PCG meetings on all aspects on all those.
aspect and of course government officials are invited to comment on these delay recovery measures.
朱直，我想問下喺呢啲P，即係喺呢個DRM measures裏邊咧，誒會involve到。
cost implications。
誒喺個制度裏邊有冇一啲好似警號噉樣樣？因為嗱，理解依之前一路就講就話呢啲DRM，因為係會用contention時，所以就唔係好擔心。
咁但係，其實喺成個設計喺個監督設計裏邊，有冇任何嘅係即係？
警報嘅系統去令到即係政府係會知道，而家用緊嘅DRM已經係消耗咗幾多嘅，即係成個高鐵工程裏邊嘅contention事。
即係嗰個。
你我並冇問題啊嘛。個cutting edge即係有個減有削減嘅話，有冇即係定期向政府報告呢一方面啊？Chairman the
在The regular, I believe, monthly reporting to government, there is.
In the papers, not just the technical aspects, not just the technical aspects of the express rail link being discussed, but the financial aspects. The financial aspects would look at the contingency remaining for the whole project. That is in the monthly reports. This two hundred plus page report, which is given to government.
我認為在他們的PSC會議之前。
主席可唔可以請係梁生提供一份typical嘅係PCG嘅即係meeting裏邊應該有嘅係文件同埋個minutes作為一個參考咧？係，梁生可唔可以提供？啊，Chairman，can I come back to the secretariat on that？好。
我有一個跟進嘅問題，就係喺呢個二零一零年，即係有關跟進問題咧。二零一零年高鐵工程開展一路到二零一四年四月期間咧。
有冇係關於呢個工程進度嘅事咧，向承建商發出任何嘅信件，包括警告信啊之類嘅，提醒佢哋要如期完成嘅工序啊？
Chairman, as I mentioned, I myself was not personally involved at that time, and so therefore the information that we have that is available would be the information from the various reports. I understand that the contractors and MTR have the same objective of completing the project as quickly as possible, and
The contractors and MTR were always looking to come up with solutions, delay recovery measures to come to try to catch up with time。其實我問題就好specific嘅，就喺二零一零年開展呢個工程，一路到二零一四年期間，有冇向承建商發出信件，包括警告信，係關於嗰個。
即係嗰個要，即係個時間嘅問題，需要keep keep個時間個time table嘅問題。Sorry, I don't have that information. I need to revert to the secretary.你翻嚟，你翻嚟覆翻我好嘛？好。
誒。
另外一個問題咧，就係有關呢個大光布，呢個係我代代呢個誒副主席問，因為佢唔喺香港。
有關呢個大江布至到鄭屋村隧道嘅工程咧，有關工程合約咧，有冇要求個承建商要做好呢個防洪閘？
如果有嘅話，咁承建商有冇履行到個相關要求咧？同埋港鐵係點樣監管個工程嗰個合約工程啊？唔該。嗯，啊。
主席，我我唔係工程一個工程專家。我嘅項目同事會喺一個月嘅時間內出庭，我會請主席容許我，我會請佢哋回答呢個問題。或者係佢哋。
誒上嚟之前，你可唔可以書面答覆我呢個呢個好嘛？呢方面唔該你。Yes, Chairman.
曾不如。
都係主席咁喺早前嘅誒，即係上一次嘅聆訊當中咧，阿誒閣下咧都係表示誒，你哋港鐵嘅團隊對於追回進度咧係誒過分樂觀嘅。咁誒呢個過分樂觀同埋專業判斷，你係點樣覺得有咩分別咧？
另外就係誒，你覺得港鐵喺做呢單工程，除咗以上即係你所謂嘅誒過分樂觀之外，仲有冇其他嘅不足地方咧？
Thank you for that question. Once again, the overoptimism unfortunately led to a late reporting of the delay. The optimism, overoptimism, really is with hindsight. I think at any point in time, the project's team.
We're working very professionally to try to catch up with schedules. This is a comment which, to go from the IUP report again, saying that the contract management was exemplary. The project team always, and even today, would do their utmost to catch up with schedule to.
Come up with solutions to catch up with the schedules. I think ultimately the success of some of those earlier solutions, the delay recovery measures, may with hindsight have led to the overoptimism of the team and the previous.
Projects Director。
All throughout the the process, the MTR projects team has remained.
In my view, very professional. They have done whatever they can to catch up time. They have worked hard. They have done everything possible to reach the objective of delivering based on a schedule and in the most cost-effective manner.
okay。
誒或者噉樣問啦，誒港鐵喺誒發現有疑誤嘅情況之下，有冇嘗試向承建商施壓？你施壓嘅方法係點樣咧？
兩三。
The.
with。
contractors the contractors and ourselves have the same objective the we work with the contractor and of course that working with the contractor are at one point in time would be giving them pressure other points in time collaborating but it is working with the contractors to deliver the project are based
on a schedule and in most cost-effective manner. It is working with the contractor.
on issues like delay recovery measures that.
allows that had allowed the project earlier on to mitigate some of the delays which could have arisen because of the construction difficulties.
OK。
另外，我想問下咧，就係誒。
即係我知你唔係technical嗰方面嘅朋友啦，咁但係誒，亦都係我想知道一下咧，就係港鐵幾時知道誒地底嗰個情況係出現問題，係比較難誒，即係掘落去或者下面啲岩石好多嘅，你哋幾時知道有冇即時通知？
誒，即係政府嗰方面，你哋係幾時通知咧？長彬議員，你講係邊一度嘅地底？誒，西九龍總站嘅地底嚇，唔該，梁生。誒，as as I understand it and and as the honourable member mentioned, I'm not the construction expert, but as I understand it from the various reports, the issue
of ground conditions.
arose actually at quite an early stage in the construction process, and as I based on all the reports available, the issues were.
reported in the various reports to to government and made a made available to the M and V consultant。誒好啦，咁既然你知道西九龍總站下低嗰啲石係咁難去誒破啦，噉你亦都係採取啲追回進度措施。你認為你嘅追回進度措？
師咧有冇誒發揮到作用咧？啊，Chairman，as I mentioned，啊，the the difficulties were啊，or the construction difficulties，the ground conditions were known。
Website investigation as well as after construction commence. However, the
situation where, for instance, the site conditions, the ground conditions, was worse than one had anticipated during the site investigation.
The project team is a very professional project team. When they come up with these problems, they come up with solutions to address the problems. So highlighted in the response to the select committee in August of this year, there were a number of instances where on the
West Kowloon terminus site, because of difficult ground conditions, there were delay recovery measures implemented. A number of those delay recovery measures were successful after implementation.
既然誒你講到你個team好專業啦，咁誒，我想問一問咧，就係按照啊路政署。
誒鐵路拓展處阿處長陳志恩先生咧，佢喺十月二十號喺言訊上面表示咧，八一一B號合約嘅工程咧，因為護土牆建造嘅工程係有所延誤嘅，噉啊，因而咧影響係八一零A嗰個工程合約嘅展開嘅。
但係喺八一零A嗰個工程合約簽署嘅時候咧，港鐵係並冇將八一零A嘅合約完成嘅日期咧，係適當咁延後嘅。
點解會噉樣咧？另外就係你係咪好相信你唔推後嗰個八一零A嘅完工日期咧？係會用你嗰啲啊好專業嘅追回進度措施，係可以追回得到啊有關嘅疑誤咧？定係誒基本上你哋係誒？
睇漏眼啊？定係有啲咩任何嘅原因？可唔可以講解一下？梁生，啊，no，I think I thank for that question. As as mentioned，the 810，the 810A contract was tendered out later than originally anticipated，and part of that was due to the some delay.
In 810B contract, the
when those when 810A 810A was tendered out, there were a number of tenders, the tenders.
Are very well aware of the programme to complete their particular the A Ten A contract, and the tenderers were of the view that the programme is achievable. So it is not just MTOS view, but the tenderers who are tendering for those contracts.
We're tendering on the basis of that particular timetable.
即係誒，你哋係相信佢哋係覺得有可能可以做得到嘅誒，還是係你哋嘅專業判斷覺得係啊噉樣批出去呢個工程，即使之前嗰個工程未完未完成，延即係延誤咗後面嗰個工程，你哋都覺得個判斷。
係可以將呢個工程唔延後咁派出去，你係純粹係相信個contractor嘅時間表係咪啊？啊，That.
We were of the view that the eight ten A in this particular case contract can be achieved or can be completed in that shortened time frame, and the tenders not just the successful tender but all the tenders that were.
tendering for this particular contract, we also have the view that the timetable, as understand, that the timetable was achievable. 嗨，what sorry，唔好意思，想想乜嘢？我想問一問就係嗰啲誒tenders佢哋去誒去入標嗰時咧，佢哋係知唔知道個嗰個？
個即係個地下嘅環境係咁複雜嘅，但係佢哋只係只係基於你哋嗰個即係勘測嗰個報告咧，去做呢個投標。
噉啊，根本就唔知道裏邊咧，原來咁有成八萬幾個個平方米嘅花崗巖嘅，係喺埋在喺地溝裏邊嘅，係咪會唔會有噉嘅情況啊？Chairman, thank for that question. The, as members are aware, MTR, we are to use our processes, including our conditions of contract. Our conditions of contract
Would have certain risk being retained by the owner of the project and certain risk passed on to the contractor. In this case, for A Ten A, the contractors A Ten A would be given the the ground investigations and ground report for.
從The investigations that have been done previously, and they would tender based on that ground investigation and that ground report.個ground report係你哋公司做嘅係嘛？This is the site investigation report, Chairman. The if the ground conditions.
Are shown to be worse than that base case report which they tender on. Than the risk rest with the owner of the project. This is the MTR standard contract terms.
誒，主席，我想問得，我想問得一條咧，就係誒，我想問下咧，港鐵咧就好相信你嗰啲追回進度嘅措施啦。咁按你嘅評估，你嘅追回進度措施係誒大概幾多個percent到係發揮到作用，定係嗰啲追回進度措施基本上？
都係會再係誒，即係延後嘅，或者係會令到個工程延誤咧。咁誒，你相信你啲追追回進度措施係基於往績啊，定係你純粹係相信你嘅即係工程隊伍咧？
梁生，嗯，Thank you, Member for that question.
I do not have, and it is very difficult to.
Assess the DRM's in that way. Whenever an very delaying issue or an issue arises, the project team, in their professional manner, would look at methodologies to overcome those issues. The important thing is to stop any further delay.
For instance, in the programme or further cost overruns, the important thing is to move a particular contract back into the original contract duration. And these DRMs, many of these DRMs were done for exactly that purpose. Some of these DRMs were quite significant. For instance, the in
One of the in 810A, there was the shifting of the Jordan Road southwards as one of the temporary traffic measures before shifted northwards. That was one of the delay recovery measures because of the difficult ground conditions that led to the difficulties on the retaining wall.
That was being built in that area. There are many other examples of successful DRM's.
但係誒，雖然係誒有啲地方係會有有成功可以做到啦，咁但係亦都有有唔少嘅，但係你又冇個數據喎，咁誒你係憑乜嘢去相信誒你嗰啲DLM措施係唔會影響個進度，而進而咧係誒影響個員工嘅期？咁即係你有冇曾經諗過？
個其實你啲D L M誒做落去係會有問題而引起誒影響個員工日期。你曾你哋港鐵有冇諗過係？
喺即係二零一四年之前，你哋有冇諗過係會有delay呢樣嘢？係問得好清楚，劉生簡短啲答案。Chairman，the thank you for that question. The as I mentioned to members and as highlighted in the reports, prior to April two thousand and fourteen, the executive of
NTR， except the then projects director and the board of NTR was not aware of the delay beyond 2015.
好，啊，第二輪。
誒五分鐘連問連答。
阿盧偉國二。
誒多幾隻。
嗯。
我想，主席，我想問阿梁生咧，就梁生喺先前嘅。
誒七月嘅十五號嘅言訊裏邊都表示咧，就係二二零一五年八月四號係高鐵香港段項目移交嘅預算日，但係佢亦都強調咧係一個預算啫。咁喺佢嘅陳述書裏邊咧，第三十二段咧。
誒或者我我我讀出嚟咧，其實佢有啲字眼係咁講嘅，就話喺第二份委託協議協議下邊咧，並無施加需喺二零一五年八月四日前完成高鐵項目嘅絕對義務，就反而咧喺呢個協議下咧，佢講嘅字眼。
就話港鐵公司須盡最大努力，根據委託計劃完成或促使完成高鐵項目，並減少任何疑問嘅影響。委託計劃可因應事變而作出修正。
包括。
括話作為一項權利，基於承建商嘅延誤而導致承建商需要延長時間要履行其責任噉樣。我我想問問啊啊梁生咧，就呢一個理解咧，係咪港鐵公司本身？
單方嘅理解咧，亦或咧，港鐵公司同埋政府咧，都係有一個共同嘅理解。
咁誒，即係誒變咗就係話咧，是否即係雙方都係覺得咧呢個係一個誒即係預算啫？噉係呢個責任上咧，就究竟係點樣嚟定嘅咧？噉樣，我哋清楚係你哋同政府有共識，呢個只係一個預算定係點樣樣？
嗯。
議員，The。
政府的own IEP報告也設出非常清楚的責任，分別是各個參與方，包括MTR和政府，根據委託協議。它也設出有關時間表和完成成本的計算方法和機制，這些時間表。
and the cost to complete can be adjusted, and therefore the
August 2015 original programme to complete is, as highlighted in the various reports, an estimate that can be subject to change. This is well highlighted in government's own IEP report, Chairman.
主席，冇進一步提問。
胡志偉議員。
多謝主席。誒，我兩條啫。第一個咧，我想問下，誒，因為今日今日阿梁生嗰個嘅係回應咧，就有就講得好清楚啦。佢就係話誒。
勞工短缺咧，係對於五條鐵路嘅係計劃咧都有好大影響嘅。噉就包括咗呢個高鐵嘅項目。咁但係我哋見到嘅結果咧就啲唔同嘅，因為呢五條嘅係鐵路咧，誒。
高鐵咧係嚴重嘅有延誤嘅現象，甚至係超支得非常之驚人。
其他嘅項目咧，就算有延誤都好啦，都唔係太過長時間。我想問下就係呢五條鐵路喺嗰個遇到人手短缺嘅問題，佢係用咗乜嘢嘅方法咧？係去即係克服。
相應嘅困難，而令到其他嘅鐵路線咧係可以如期，或者只係延短嘅時間就完成，亦都係喺預定budget之內完成。但係偏偏就係即係高鐵就唔得咧，咁呢個第一。
第二個其實喺上一次我有一個提問咧，就關於因為梁生一路強調就係話喺過往嘅會議，其實政府好即係誒誒Executive Committee都好啦，佢哋都係好掌握到成個工程個造價嘅改變嘅誒。
係有任何嘅係追趕落後、追趕而唔嘅措施，都所牽涉嘅相關成本都係知，只不過就係話喺二零一四年嘅四月。
公佈嗰個港鐵即係高鐵超支之前咧，一路都覺得就係話嗰個嘅應急嘅費用咧係足以應付。
我今日都仍然追問呢一點啦，即係中間嗰個變化嚟得咁急，由本嚟足夠變成喺二零一四年四月之後啊，突然間係唔足夠。
即係呢個係唔係一個突然突如其來嘅知嘅信息，還是其實之前都係有一啲跡象嘅，而啲跡象咧係喺政府嘅資料裏邊咧係掌握到嘅。
梁生。
嗯哼，嗯哼。
主席，首先，我會 Highlight that in fact the.
many or unfortunately all our existing rail projects are and have suffered some degree of delay, and some of those apart from the express rail link and some of those have been not insignificant. As members are aware, the
Quinton line extension and the South Island line East, which are currently projects ongoing, have also suffered delays and have also suffered from the some of the common issues and common problems across the industry, which includes the shortage of labour. We have disclosed and announced the latest.
estimate of the cost to complete and the programme to complete for those other ownership projects, and I think members would find that in terms of the cost to complete, the there has also been unfortunately some increases in costs which of a magnitude that.
May not be dissimilar to the increases that we're talking about for the Express Rail Link. So there have been some costs and programme implications because of the common issues that pertain to the construction industry here in Hong Kong. I would secondly add that the Express Rail Link itself is.
作為成員所知，係一個非常複雜的項目。係世界上第一個或地下或地下高速鐵路項目，我認為。而西九龍終端站，它佔地11公頃，我認為有建設面積38萬平方公尺。
米，它是一個非常非常大的項目，which adds to the complexity.
The.
Member, second question with regards to the increase in cost situation for the Express Rail Link, as highlighted in the various reports and confirmed in all our reporting, up until March of 2014. Up until March of 2014, the Express Rail Link
budget was still showing a contingency amount. In fact, up until March of 2014, the amount of contingency shown was around 3.75, 3.75 billion Hong Kong dollars. That was on the basis of
The.
project being able to meet its
original timetable.
In April of two thousand and fourteen, a month after that, as members are aware, the executive of MTR, apart from the project director, the board of MTR became aware of the was made aware of the delay in the schedule. As a result of that, the our teams were asked to do.
做一個評估，對完成的費用。一個延誤，一個延誤會增加費用。所以因此，直到2014年3月，預算仍然顯示一個。
contingency based on the old timetable to complete of August 2015.
With the delay, that delay would increase costs, and therefore it is because of that delay which has increased the cost of the express rail link beyond the original budget.
嗱，就誒。
或者係最後一個問題，或者我問一問阿梁生啦。
就係根據你嗰個嗱，通常我嘅理解咧，一般嘅工程咧。
都係有個期限嘅。
咁過咗呢個期限啊，可能會有即係罰則啊之類之類嗰啲噉嘅嘢。
咁而家聽梁生正話畀嘅政工咧，就話呢個誒誒一五年八月呢個期限咧，其實只係一個預測嚟嘅啫。咁喺機制上咧係可以更改呢個期限嘅。
咁換句話嚟講，噉我噉樣理解啱唔啱？其實呢個整個工程咧就係冇期限嘅，只係有一個預測嘅啫。即係你個你個工程幾時起好就幾時起好，所以呢個就係期限，係咪噉樣理解咧？係咪應該噉樣樣去理解咧？
Thank you, Chairman. The under the entrustment agreement, which is well highlighted in the IEP report, it does note that the
啊，the program to complete is an estimate that is subject and that can be changed under certain circumstances。係我我即係我唔理個回覆，我我係問一問，我個問題係畀你，唔係畀個panel。即係嚇個問題係咪？即係我噉樣理解啱唔啱？即係呢個呢個根本就係冇期限呢個呢個呢個工程合約。
就你幾時起好就幾時起好，因為嗰個只係一個預測嚟啫。嗯，Chairman，we always use our best endeavours to complete the project as quickly as possible under the entrustment agreements. But the entrustment agreement itself has the programme to complete as an estimate that is and can be subject to change.
係你要你要做最大嘅努力去完成咩工程，但係你幾時完成咧？就係幾時就係完成工程㗎啦，就冇一個期限嘅，係咪啊？即係你到二零二零年、二零二八年都係可以咁做嘅。
主席，你知，once again the。
program in the entrustment agree the program in the entrustment agreement is an estimate, and that estimate is subject to adjustments under certain circumstances. We, as the project manager, manager, always use our best endeavours to complete the project in as shorter time as possible.係，但係就冇一個期限嘅。
係咪噉嘅意思？我理解啱唔啱咧？The the programme under the the estimated programme under the entrustment agreement is, 啊，subject to adjustment in accordance with the entrustment agreement, chairman.
唔係，所以我就問你係咪個entrustment agreement裏邊咧係冇一個期限嘅？
啊！
主席，The Entrustment Agreement requires MTR to use its best endeavours to in our project management. and the唔係阿梁生個問題就係你有冇一個期限，你都要use best endeavours㗎啦，用最要盡最大嘅努力㗎啦。但係問題嚟講就係，即係係咪我個問題好簡單，亦都係好。
就係係咪冇一個限期嘅？其實呢個investment agreement。
I think under the IEP report, it very clearly sets out that there are mechanisms to amend the entrustment programme, and those mechanisms are very clear, Chairman.
okay。
O.K.或者係誒，我諗。
冇其他問題嘅話咧，個會議結束嚇。噉啊，梁生誒，多謝你。就如果有需要嘅話，我希望冇咁需要。
咁專責委員會再邀請你哋誒出席言言訊，而家你可以退席啦。再次多多謝你出席呢次言訊。唔該曬主席。